<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prosecution no persecution, or, The difference between suffering for disobedience and faction, and suffering for righteousness and Christ's sake truly discussed and stated in a sermon upon Phil. I. 29, preached at Bury St. Edmunds in Suffolk on the 22th of March, 1681, being the time of the general assizes there held / by Nath. Bisbie ...</title>
            <author>Bisbie, Nathaniel, 1635-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28223</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2983</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18612</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12258232</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12258232</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57621</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28223)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57621)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 167:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prosecution no persecution, or, The difference between suffering for disobedience and faction, and suffering for righteousness and Christ's sake truly discussed and stated in a sermon upon Phil. I. 29, preached at Bury St. Edmunds in Suffolk on the 22th of March, 1681, being the time of the general assizes there held / by Nath. Bisbie ...</title>
                  <author>Bisbie, Nathaniel, 1635-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Freedom of religion --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Great Britain --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57621:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57621:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> PROSECUTION NO PERSECUTION: Or, the Difference Between Suffering for <hi>Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> and <hi>Faction,</hi> AND Suffering for <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt's Sake;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly Diſcuſſed and Stated.</p>
            <p>IN A SERMON Upon <hi>PHIL.</hi> 1. 29.</p>
            <p>Preached at <hi>Bury St. Edmunds</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> on the 22<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1681. being the time of the general <hi>Aſſizes</hi> there held.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Nath. Bisbie,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1682.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:57621:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:57621:2"/>
            <head>To my ever honoured Patron Sir <hi>John Cordell</hi> of <hi>Long Melford</hi> Baronet, one of His Majeſties Deputy Lieutenants for the County of <hi>Suffolk;</hi> and to the Vertuous and truly Religious Lady, Dame <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his Wife, <hi>Continuance of Health, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Happineſs.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHen this Sermon was firſt Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched it was vulgarly ſaid, that it was boldly done; but (if I miſtake not) it is much more bold and daring to cauſe it to be made publick. Speed it as it may, I am ſufficiently pleaſed that in this juncture of Affairs (when Allegiance is made a Crime, and Conformity little better than In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity,) I have Patrons able and ready to aſſert the intereſt of them both; The one a lineal deſcendant of my Original Patron, and
<pb facs="tcp:57621:3"/> I hope Succeſſion in this caſe is no ways Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal; the other of a Family no leſs Loyal, and if that be Criminal I beg no ones pardon. My Prayer is, and ever ſhall be, That none of you may degenerate, or in the leaſt be tempted to look awry; and howbeit others are too too apt to deſpiſe the Prieſthood, (and perhaps the more becauſe they are Loyal and True to <hi>David</hi> and his Family,) yet may the Bleſſing thereof always deſcend upon you, and upon all that deſcend from, or belong unto you; and this is, and ſhall be the daily Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull and ready Servant, in all Prieſtly Offices, and humble Gratitude, <hi>Nath. Bisbie.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Long Melford. Suff. <date>29 May. 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57621:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PHIL. 1. 29.</bibl>
               <q>For unto you it is given in the behalf of Chriſt, not only to believe on him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HE that would gain upon his Auditory, and win the Attentions and Affections of the people, muſt not onely be (as the Orator ſaith) ready and prepared to ſpeak; but he muſt do it ſeaſonably and ſutably to the matter and duty of the day: Inſomuch that this Lenten Faſt ſhould have a Lenten Sermon; and you indeed hear of nothing, but Faſtings, Watchings, Penanceings, together with the more ſevere Doctrines of Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Repentance. The Preacher ſhould have come (like the Baptiſt) clad in his Rayment of Camels hair, and been the voice of one crying in the Wilderneſs, prepare ye the way of the Lord, and make his paths ſtraight: But conſidering withall the confluxe of people, and the more than uſual Solemnity of the time, I thought good to change my Subject, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Repentance to preach up Faith, inſtead of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanceing to encourage unto Sufferings. And certainly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57621:4"/> whoſoever will but ſeriouſly conſider the Preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Church, how it is oppos'd by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts on the one hand, and the Phanaticks (their Sworn Brethren in iniquity) on the other, as if it were a Den of Thieves rather than a Church of God; as alſo how the Miniſters and Managers thereof are diſcouraged, flouted, maligned; paſſing ſometimes under the name of the Prophane, at other times under the hated ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation of Papiſts, (though as to the one, they may as well be <hi>Jews;</hi> and as to the other Devils) may conclude it a task not unſutable to the day, to ſet forth the true nature of Suffering, in oppoſition to the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſentations that are made of it in the World; and to encourage you (who are of the Communion of the Church) to ſtand firm and conſtant to the Faith that hath been delivered to you: So that though the World frown, and throw its ſlavor and indignities upon you, you may notwithſtanding bear and ſuffer all, rather than deſert her eſtabliſhment, founded by your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors in a bleſſed and deſirable Reformation; and not only Heroically and Chriſtianly by them defended, but by their Sufferings and Martyrdoms propagated and handed down to us, and ours. In ſhort, There are Two things that all vertuous and good men ever have, always ought, and at all times will carefully labour after; and upon no account whatſoever be diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in, or frighted from; and they are, To do well, and to Suffer ill; To be true to God, dutifull to their Sovereign, honeſt and juſt one to the other; and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than do otherwiſe, to endure any hardſhip; The rough hands of <hi>Eſau;</hi> the gainſayings of <hi>Corah;</hi> the afflictions, neceſſities, diſtreſſes, ſtripes, bonds, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> endured. This was the great commendation of the <hi>Philippians</hi> in my Text, <hi>For unto</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:57621:4"/> 
               <hi>you it is given in the behalf of Chriſt not only to believe on him but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which Words,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Perſons Commended, You <hi>Philippians, To you it is given.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The Things they are Commended for, and that is, Firſt for their Faith, <hi>To you it is given to believe in him:</hi> Secondly, For their Fortitude: <hi>To you it is given in the behalf of Chriſt, not only to believe in him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Begin we</p>
            <p>Firſt, With the Perſons Commended; You, <hi>To you it is given;</hi> or (as it is Ver. 1.) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, To you the Saints at, in, or about <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippi;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with the Biſhops and Deacons there; <hi>To you it is given:</hi> To you the Saints, <hi>Qui Sanctitate ſaltem Sacramentali ſancti,</hi> who have been Hallowed and Sanctified into a Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> through Baptiſm in his Name, <hi>To you it is given:</hi> Yet not ſo as if your Biſhops and Deacons (who have not only the ſame, but by virtue of their Office and Order a further Sanctification) were not alike Holy, or alike Saints. This were to have infus'd into them a Spirit of Pride and Scorn, like that of the Saint-like <hi>Jews, (Iſa.</hi> 65. 5.) to cry out, <hi>Stand by thy ſelf, come not near me, for I am holier than thou;</hi> and really to have planted in them the Factious Seditious Humor which was found in <hi>Corah,</hi> and his Fellow Schiſmaticks, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Aaron</hi> and the reſt of the Prieſthood, <hi>(Numb.</hi> 16. 13.) <hi>You take too much upon you, ſeeing all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation is holy;</hi> Crimes too too incident now adays to the inferiour and more ordinary ſort of Believers. No, To you the Saints with the Biſhops and Deacons; To you the Saints at large, To them the Biſhops and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57621:5"/> Deacons in particular, and by name; giving the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour moſtly to the laſt, and making the laſt in place to be the firſt in Suffering: thereby ſhewing, that if the true Faith (the Faith that was by the Apoſtles firſt planted in the Church) be to be kept up, the Biſhops and Clergy muſt be the men by name that do it: Or if Perſecution chance to ariſe, either from Enemies without, or from falſe Teachers or Brethren within, they muſt be the <hi>Anteſignani,</hi> the firſt in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict, and the Leaders on of the reſt; it being natural to the Churches Enemies (under what denomination ſoever they fight) to fix their malice upon the Clergy, and to charge their Complices (as the King of <hi>Syria</hi> did his Captains) to fight neither againſt ſmall nor great, but only againſt them: But certainly it is never better for the Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (be it at <hi>Philippi,</hi> or elſe where) then for the Saints to be with their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Deacons, in conjuction and communion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, both as to Faith and Suffering. There is a Baptiſm in Bloud, as well as a Baptiſm in Water; but then it is right, and as it ſhould be, when Prieſt and People (like <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt with his Saviour in his hands) go down into the Flood together to be Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with that Baptiſm: I mean, when the People and the Prieſt joyn hand in hand, both in the Defence of, and in the Suffering for the Faith delivered to them: The Believers in their Station, and the Miniſters in theirs; all and every one earneſtly contending for the Defence and Continuance of the ſame; and rather than give place to any, or ſuffer it to periſh from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, to periſh themſelves under it; that out of their Aſhes and overthrow (for <hi>ſanguis Martyrum eſt ſemen Eccleſiae)</hi> a new Phaenix (a new Poſterity of Believers) may ariſe; <hi>To you it is thus given, not</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57621:5"/> 
               <hi>only to believe on Chriſt, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake.</hi> For though Perſecution be the Portion of the Saints in general, the Legacy which our dying Saviour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath'd unto them; for hanging upon the Croſs (ſaith St. <hi>Ambroſe)</hi> he made his Will, bequeathing his Body to the <hi>Jews,</hi> his Spirit to his Father, his Mother to the beloved Apoſtle, Paradiſe to the Thief, Hell to Sinners, and Perſecution to his Saints and Followers: Though this (I ſay) be the lot of all Chriſtians, and of the Church in general; yet, to you, to you of the Church at <hi>Philippi,</hi> or (as St. <hi>Polycarp</hi> in the Title of his Epiſtle to the ſaid <hi>Philippians</hi> phraſeth it,) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>To you of the Church of God lying near or belonging to the Church at</hi> Philippi, (making it thereby to be a Metropolitical Church, with many Biſhops and Deacons in it, the only reaſon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps why Biſhops are here mentioned in the Plural number) To you the Saints and Biſhops at <hi>Philippi; To you it is given,</hi> that is, To you it is a Gift, a moſt Royal gift, a ſpecial Grace, not a Burthen, but an Honour and Privilege. <hi>To you</hi> eminently and above other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <hi>it is given, not only to believe, but alſo to ſuffer for Chriſts ſake;</hi> ſutable to that ſaying of our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>(Math.</hi> 13. 11.) <hi>To you it is given to know the myſteries of the Kingdom of heaven, but to them it is not given.</hi> Other Churches may have other Gifts confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon them (other Excellencies and other Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that may make them lovely,) and perhaps in ſome meaſure this of Suffering too; but it is your par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Endowment, the Grace which God (out of his ſignal favour) hath deſigned for, and entailed upon you; even this, To believe well, and to ſuffer ill; to do right, and to endure wrong; to proſecute that which is good and well-pleaſing unto God, and to be proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57621:6"/> for it. And here in order to the proſecution of my deſign from theſe Words, it will not be amiſs to ſet forth the condition of the Saints at <hi>Philippi,</hi> when the Apoſtle wrote this Epiſtle to them, that we may know how theſe Sufferings came upon them; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what account their Faith, and adherence to that Faith came to be ſo perſecuted, and ſo commended. And you muſt know</p>
            <p>Firſt, That they came to be Saints by an Apoſtle; and by no leſs an one than St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the great Doctor of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> who in the time of his travails into <hi>Macedonia</hi> converted them, and firſt framed them into a Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſaid therefore to be his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his firſt Fruits in that Region; for <hi>(Acts</hi> 16. 9.) A Viſion appeared to him in the Night, and there ſtood a man of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> and prayed him, ſaying, come over into <hi>Macedonia;</hi> and ſo looſing from <hi>Troas,</hi> he came to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothracia,</hi> and the next day to <hi>Neapolis,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Philippi;</hi> where (preaching the Goſpel) he firſt founded them into a Church, leaving it and them to the inſpection and government of Biſhops, and their reſpective Deacons; as may be ſeen at large in the fourteenth Chapter of the <hi>Acts,</hi> and more particularly in the twenty third Verſe thereof; an uſage cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in all places wherever he came. And indeed to ſee a Church without a Biſhop is as monſtrous in Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, as in Nature to ſee a Body without an Head; and (if by Faction or Violence diſpoiled of them) much like that ſad and never to be forgotten Spectacle of our late Martyred Sovereign, a Royal Trunk, with an Head chopt of, lying bleeding by. Such Aſſemblies as theſe were called of old <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>headleſs Churches,</hi> or Churches without an Head; neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed can the Saints of themſelves regularly make a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57621:6"/> Church, no nor Saints though in conjunction with their Deacons; <hi>To you the Saints at</hi> Philippi, <hi>with the Biſhops and Deacons, Grace be unto you, and Peace from God our Father, and from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> A ſtrange thing therefore, That that which compleats a Church, and makes it beautiful, perfect, glorious, ſhould ſeem to deſtroy a Church, and be made the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grievance of the Saints; when in truth and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed no Apoſtolical Church, ſcarce a Saint (of the Primitive ſtamp and beauty) can be found without them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Church thus eſtabliſhed was ſoon overrun with Errour, Hereſie and Schiſm, (the great Peſts of Chriſtianity, and the moſt certain Forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to the ill being and perſecution of the Saints.) And here two ſorts of men will be found highly Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Falſe Teachers.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Schiſmatical Brethren, too too apt to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thoſe Falſe Teachers.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Falſe Teachers, and theſe the Apoſtle calleth Dogs, (Ch. 3. v. 2.) <hi>Beware of Dogs.</hi> Not dumb Dogs, (that's the Title they are pleaſed to give unto the more Regular Clergy, becauſe forſooth not ſo forward to open upon every Scent, and to follow with full cry every falſe Trail that the crafty Huntſman ſhams them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,) but barking and biting Dogs, always yelping and exclaiming againſt the Orthodox Profeſſors, taking on upon all occaſions (eſpecially againſt their Biſhops, Deacons, and Governors) as ill natur'd Curs do at the Moon; or rather at the Man in it, becauſe they fear he inſpects their manners, and will one day call them to account for their Night irregularities. The Learned <hi>Hammond</hi> makes Two Sorts of them; Firſt,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57621:7"/> Heretical Gnoſticks, and Secondly, Judaizing Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. The firſt a Sort of illuminated and gifted Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ready to veer and turn about with any Wind rather than to weather out a Storm: The other, old Ceremonialiſts, obſerving ſtill the Moſaical Law, and requiring all to Judaize with them, or elſe perſecuting them for it. The Apoſtle ſpeaking of them both, (Ch. 1. v. 15.) telleth us, That they preach <hi>Chriſt</hi> out of envy, ſtrife, and contention: <hi>Soboles contentioſa &amp; ad rixas nata,</hi> (as one ſaith of them;) a Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (a brood of men) much like that of <hi>Cadmus;</hi> ariſing out of Serpents teeth, and naturally hiſſing, ſtinging, poyſoning themſelves and others: Born (I may ſay) with Flambeaus in their hands, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd like <hi>Eroſtratus</hi> to Fire the Temple of the Gods, though themſelves periſh in the Flame. Nay, delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with <hi>Nero</hi> in the Fire they have kindled, and (though their own Houſes be next, yet) ſtand Sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Religiouſly by with Anthems and Hymns to the good ſucceſs of the Flames. The Apoſtle in the ſame breath calleth them Evil-workers: Workers, and in the work of the Goſpel, (Preaching daily, and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing earneſtly) but not out of good mind, and for the intereſt of the Church, but Maliciouſly, Selfiſhly; and thereby ſuppoſing (they are the Apoſtles own words, Ch. 1. v. 16.) <hi>to add Afflictions to his Bonds;</hi> greater trouble by their Schiſm and Diſſent, (by their unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Preachings and Aſſemblings) than otherwiſe the bare Profeſſion and Managery of Chriſtianity would expoſe its Followers unto. <hi>Beware of Dogs, beware of evil Worerks, beware of the Conciſion;</hi> men pretending to be of the Circumciſion, but are indeed of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion; and in the number of thoſe that do <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, cut and tare the Church in ſunder. A threefold Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veat;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57621:7"/> Firſt, beware of them, as you would of a mad Dog, that foams and ſlavers, bites and infects all that come near him. Beware of them Secondly, as you would of thoſe that deſign upon you, no leſs than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt life; nay, upon your Faith dearer than that life. Laſtly, beware of them, as you would of men who come with Knives or Sciſſers in their hand, to cut and to mangle all they have to do with; rending and taring the Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (that Seamleſs Coat of his) into Rags and Tatters, till they do make of that lovely Garment, a long ill patch'd Cloak for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their Covetouſneſs, Hypocriſie, Ambition.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Sort of Criminals in the caſe are,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Schiſmatical Brethren, too too apt to follow thoſe Falſe Teachers; and theſe the Apoſtle moſt pathetically exhorts to Unity, as looking upon it to be the beſt expedient to preſerve the Faith, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the Church which he had planted among them. <hi>If there be any conſolation in Chriſt</hi> (ſaith he, Ch. 2. Ver. 1. 2.) <hi>if any comfort of love, if any fellowſhip of the Spirit, if any bowels and mercy, fulfill yee my joy, that ye be like minded, having the ſame love, being of one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and of one mind.</hi> And in truth nothing in the world promotes Religion more than Unity, nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves it ſooner than Diviſions. <hi>If ye bite and devour one another,</hi> (Gal. 5. 15.) <hi>take heed that you be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed.</hi> Certainly no Popiſh Conſpiracy, no Factious ASSOCIATION could ever hurt us, if we did not cheriſh and maintain them by our Diviſions: Nay, truth it ſelf may be the Judge in this caſe, <hi>(Luc.</hi> 11. 17.) <hi>An houſe divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand:</hi> Which calls to mind that Apologue or Story of <hi>Beſſarion,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging the Princes againſt the <hi>Turk,</hi> and made uſe of by <hi>Melancton</hi> againſt the Papiſts: There was a War
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57621:8"/> between the Wolves and the Dogs; whereupon news coming to the Wolves that there was a mighty number of Dogs marching againſt them, intending to tare them to pieces; the Wolves ſent out one of their Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity for a Spy, who returns, that the Report was true, and the Army of them very great; but you need not (ſaith he) fear them, for they are of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Colours, and cannot agree amongſt themſelves, but ſnarl and ſnap, and fight with one another. My Prayer ſhall be much the ſame as <hi>Melancthon</hi>'s was, That the Son of God would govern us, and make us all to be of one Mind, and of one Faith in the Church; that there be no Falſe Teachers, nor no Schiſmatical Brethren; no Diviſions nor no Factions: But that we may all go up unto the Houſe of God together, and there (as it is <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 4, 5.) <hi>be one body, and one Spirit;</hi> having <hi>one Lord, one Baptiſm, one God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all.</hi> And ſo I have done with the Perſons Commended; having ſhewn who they were, and what their condition was, how troubled, and wherein diſeaſed: And from them I paſs</p>
            <p>Secondly, To the things they are commended for; and that is,</p>
            <p>Firſt, For their Faith.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For their Fortitude.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For their Faith; <hi>To you it is given in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of Chriſt to believe in him;</hi> that is, To have and maintain a ſound Faith, a Faith anſwerable and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent to the Faith preached to you, and planted with you by your Apoſtle: And <hi>to you it is given to believe,</hi> in oppoſition</p>
            <p>Firſt, To the Nullifidians, who look upon the (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or the) Higheſt revelation, as a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57621:8"/> an empty ſound, a Grecian Mythology or Roman Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gend; reducing all to reaſon, and in the end making that no better than a well contrived Mechaniſm, where if the Clock ſtrike for the wiſer ſort of men to know the time of the day (though it be but to eat, and to drink, and to play,) and to ſet others (their inferiors and dependants) to work, They think they have no more to do, nor no further account to make. Speak of Heaven, It is an <hi>Elyſian</hi> Field, and only fit for the aiery Poet to play his wanton Muſes in. Of Hell, It is no other than one of <hi>Plautus</hi> his imaginary tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Iſlands, (his <hi>fuſtitudineae, ferricrepidinae inſulae)</hi> where the Club, the Whip, and the Shackle, gives all the entertainment. The Bible, a meer extract of the more weighty Books of Conjuration (burnt by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſerv'd the old Philoſophers afore him) to make his own works more ſignificant and great; and the Preachers thereof, meer Pariſh Mormo's, ſet up by publick Authority with the Spirit in their Mouths, and the Bible in their Hands to ſcare, and to awe the more fearful and cowardly Sinners. A brave Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation indeed! But a greater piece of folly than ever appeared in the World, beſide the Fop that fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieth it; much like unto the Fly, who when a mighty Duſt was raiſed by the Coach that carried him, and by the Horſes that drew it, ſaid, See what a Duſt it is, that I make: Lo, what a conſiderable Creature the great God (if there be any) hath made me. But haſt thou a Being, then tell me (I pray thee) who gave thee thy Tongue to prattle thus? who made thee able to be thus Sawcy? and who is it (doſt thou think) if thou be any thing but a Fly, or an inſect, that will make thee work again, when once death hath put that matter out of motion? The Jews, the Heathens,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57621:9"/> the Chriſtians, the Turks (all that are, were, or ever ſhall be) generally agree in this, That there is a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtate, and a ſpecial way to attain that ſtate; and why then ſhouldſt thou (and two or three more Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks like thy ſelf) be the only faithleſs Tomboys in the world? who (like <hi>Zeno)</hi> ſhall walk and talk, prate and diſpute, and yet not believe that there is any Sence, or any Motion in Nature. <hi>To you it is given to believe in Chriſt,</hi> in oppoſition</p>
            <p>Secondly, to the Falſifidians, who will believe any thing at firſt ear, that is obtruded upon them, though loaded with never ſo many Abſurdities, never ſuch ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Solaeciſms, never ſuch ſeeming Impoſſibilities: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that they will take and adore a rotten Sign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt for the true Croſs of our Saviour; a piece of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Bread (breath'd upon by a Prieſt) for the natural Body of the eternal Son of God; believe a Deity in the work of their own hands; ſwallow down the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couth Doctrines of Tranſubſtantiation, Ubiquity, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as roundly as men do Pills. Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions oftentimes befalling Wiſemen, yet as abſurd as the apprehenſion of Fools; and as incompatible, as (for another brood of Believers among us) to ſay, That Rebellion is good Allegiance, and to be a Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick the only way to be a Saint; That to be Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious is to be Religious, and to renounce their Biſhops, and Deacons, as neceſſary as to renounce the Devil, and his Works. A Faith ſo large and prodigious, that I could be <hi>Gebal, Ammon, Amalek,</hi> and abundance of hard Names more, and yet ſet up for a True Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, or (as the word now is) a <hi>True Proteſtant.</hi> This I do find that all, and every one of theſe, will be Believers, and (in ſome degree or other) Saints into the bargain; but in truth and indeed the Turkiſh
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57621:9"/> Muſſelman (nay, Janizary) may put in for a ſhare, and (for ought as I do know) not be very much worſe Believers. <hi>To you it is given not only to believe, but to ſuffer,</hi> in oppoſition</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To the Solifidians, who will do nothing but believe: Be all Faith, no ſuffering for that Faith; all pure imagination and phanſie, without action, or the leaſt of paſſion: Like unto the Bird of Paradiſe, whoſe Nature is to be almoſt all Mouth, or all Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; Mouth to ſuck in the air for the maintenance and continuance of its Being, and Feathers to ſupport it in that air, where it lives, and feeds, and breeds. Not but that Faith gallantly doth, and valiantly re-en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countreth all difficulties; It prevaileth againſt Satan, it conquereth Sin, it hath Death in deriſion, Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and Powers muſt ſtoop under it; it leadeth the World captive, and bringeth every Enemy that riſeth up againſt it to confuſion and ſhame. What ſhall I ſay more, ſaith the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews? It ſtopped the mouths of Lions, quenched the violence of the fire, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated the edge of the ſword.</hi> And in truth, to ſay no more, it will undoubtedly quaſh the Conſults of the bloody Jeſuites; nay, fruſtrate the ASSOCIATIONS of (their elder Brother) the Church-rending and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion-confounding Puritan: But then it muſt not be alone, for if it be, <hi>It is dead,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>James.</hi> Nay, <hi>It is nothing,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul;</hi> though in this unhappy Age of ours, it goeth often for an Hereſie to add Works unto Faith, or Obedience unto <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Righteouſneſs: It being (as it were) againſt the Liberty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to preſcribe them any Rules of duty, and thereby make Slaves of Free born men; but rather ſuffer them to live, as if <hi>Chriſt</hi> had never dyed for them, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as if his Righteouſneſs and Obedience without
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57621:10"/> any act at all of their own were to be imputed to them; whereupon becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> lived innocently, and in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the Higher Powers, therefore the unruly, diſobedient Factioniſt, which is ſaid (and thinks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) to believe, muſt be accounted a good Subject, by the imputation of his Righteouſneſs and Obedience. A Doctrine, that hath ſo confounded our Church and Nation, that (I dare ſay) the Lives of ten hundred thouſand (yea, and perhaps twice times told) have been loſt; nor is that iſſue of blood yet ſtancht, but without a Miracle of providence it is like to run afreſh, and as faſt as ever. And it is remarkable, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this ſort of Believers (theſe Solifidians) take place, there Peace and Obedience to Lawful Authority have been conſtantly caſt out: It is a Sect that doth infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly bring along with it Sedition, and Tumults, and Bloodſhed; and therefore eminently deſerves to have a ſpecial mark of Reprobation ſet upon it, that you may for ever beware of it. You the People, without whoſe aid and aſſiſtance they had never been able (nor never again ſhall) to do ſuch infinite miſchiefs; and you the Deacons, without whoſe hallowed Lungs the Trumpet had never ſounded to Battel, nor ever ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Romiſh or Engliſh Hoſt been conſecrated to the deſtruction of the Church and State among us.</p>
            <p>My advice therefore to you (my Brethren and Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſtians) is</p>
            <p>Firſt, To keep unto your Faith.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To add Obedience to your Faith; that eſpecially which is due to your King, who is the true and careful Defender of your Faith.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To keep unto your Faith; a Faith every ways perfect and ſound; conſonant to the Inſtitutions, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, and Practices of the holy <hi>Jeſus;</hi> and to the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57621:10"/> Preachings and Writings of the bleſſed Apoſtles. A Faith anſwerable to that which is yet to be found in the holy Scriptures, and to that which at firſt was planted in all Churches of the World, that had an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, or Apoſtolical man for its Founder; of kin na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally, neither to the <hi>Trentine</hi> Fathers, nor to the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva</hi> Brethren; but of the blood Royal, and deſcended from <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf the eternal Son of God; foſter'd and nurs'd up by the hands of his immediate Apoſtles, and Miniſters; and in being throughout all Ages of the Church to this very day. A Faith that hath ſtood tryal through the Ten Perſecutions, endured and quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the <hi>Marian</hi> Flames, weathered out the bloodſhed and confuſions of <hi>Babel;</hi> and is ſo good and ſo ſound ſtill, that it will never want Kings to be its Defenders, nor multitude of Believers to bleed, and to dye for it. Keep (I ſay) to this Faith; neither ſcared with the damning Anathemas of the Pope, and his Catholick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as if there were no Chriſtianity out of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; nor with the pious Pretences of the whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>egig Proteſtants, as if there were no Reformation, nor Saintſhip without them. Your Cauſe is good, and the very ſame with the Primitive Chriſtians; the very ſame with your Forefathers in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days; the very ſame as it was when <hi>Cromwel,</hi> and the ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Rump, play'd the Devil in <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Name. Give not over this Faith, whatever the Poſterity of the one, or the preſent Brood of the other, threaten you withal. <hi>Juſtum &amp; tenacem propoſiti virum, non civium ardor pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va jubentium;</hi> So good, ſo accountable a Faith is not to be reprobated (no, nor deſerted) for any heat of Citizens, for any faction of Senators, for any madneſs of the People. Wherefore though the whole World almoſt (as they did in <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his days) ſhould
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57621:11"/> 
               <hi>Arrianizare,</hi> turn mad and Conventicle; nay, <hi>Si fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus illabatur orbis,</hi> Though they ſhould murther their King again, and pull the Foundations of the earth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout your ears; yet hold your own, and let it be ſaid of you in the Tranſcript as of the <hi>Philippians</hi> in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, <hi>That to you it is given in the behalf of Chriſt, not only to believe in him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My ſecond advice is</p>
            <p>Secondly, To add Obedience to your Faith; that eſpecially which is due to your King, the Defender of your Faith. It is obſerved of the defection made by the ten Tribes from the two, whereby <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> came to be two Kingdoms, that all the Levites all the Land over, as alſo all the well-affected and good men (who were not for the High places, and for the Devils, and for the Calves, which <hi>Jeroboam</hi> the Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious and Factious Uſurper had ſet up) clove to the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> and to <hi>Rehoboam</hi> their Natural and Lawfull Prince, (2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11. 13.) And it may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved further, to the eternal Honour of their Loyalty, that ſmall or no interruptions were made by them, or by their Poſterity as to the Lineal deſcent of their Kings, ſo long as they remained a Nation; though in <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſeldom above three of the ſame Stock continued in a direct Succeſſion. Nay, further, <hi>Judah</hi> had but two Tribes to ten for the ſupport of their King and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and yet <hi>Iſrael</hi> that were ten to two were long deſtroyed and captivated before them; Loyalty being certainly a moſt ſure and laſting Bulwark againſt all Deſolations. And in good ſooth, if any thing keeps up our Religion, ſo that <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> his High pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, his Devils, and his Calves, do not utterly devour us, it muſt be our Integrity and Loyalty to our King: Loyalty, the unqueſtionable duty of all good Subjects,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57621:11"/> and of all the ſincere Worſhippers of the true God: Loyalty, the fondling and darling of Princes, which will make us be beloved and defended by our Kings; and at laſt will prove the ſureſt Preſervative to our Church againſt Confuſion, and the likelieſt Remedy to reſtore it, and give it a Reſurrection if it ſhould ever happen to be overlaid. It is always proſperous and victorious; it hath the favour of Kings here, and the reward of the King of Kings hereafter: It gives us Crowns, becauſe we love the Crown; and it will make us Kings in another World, for being good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in this. Think not then that Loyalty will hurt you; or that your being and continuing faithful to your King, and his rightful Succeſſors, ſhall ever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dammage your Religion: A Religion ſo eminent for its Allegiance, and ſo hitherto unattainted, that God's Vicegerents (as long as they love their Regality) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, will not ſuffer it to be oppreſs'd. <hi>If you aim at a</hi> Scotiſh <hi>Presbytery</hi> (ſaith King <hi>James) it agreeth as well with Monarchy, as God and the Devil; then</hi> Jack <hi>and</hi> Tom, <hi>and</hi> Will <hi>and</hi> Dick, <hi>ſhall meet and cenſure Me and my Council; I may thank you (my Biſhops) that theſe men plead for my Supremacy: But if once you were out, and they in, I know not what would become of my Supremacy, for NO BISHOP NO KING. One of the greateſt faults ſome men found with the COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MON-PRAYER BOOK</hi> (ſaith King <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr) <hi>was this, that it taught them to pray ſo oft for Me; to which Petitions they had not Loyalty enough to ſay Amen. No Church in the World</hi> (ſaith our preſent Sovereign) <hi>hath Taught and Practiſed LOYALTY ſo Conſcientiouſly as the Church of</hi> England <hi>hath done. Experience hath ſhewn</hi> (ſaith the preſent Heir, the only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Bugbear, to a ſort of Mungrel
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57621:12"/> Proteſtants) <hi>That the Members of the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>are the beſt Supporters of the Crown, inſomuch that if it fall to Him to be concerned, he will ever counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and preſerve Them, and It.</hi> Wherefore let re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter Fears keep remoter off; and as we are bound, by the 37th. Article of our Religion, to give that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative to our King, which was given to the Godly Princes in Scripture: Let us likewiſe give the ſame Loyalty as they did; ſuch (I mean) as <hi>Judah</hi> and her Brethren gave to their Kings and Princes; and I doubt not but by ſo doing, if ever we go into Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, our King muſt with us. And ſo I have finiſhed the firſt branch of their commendation, <hi>viz.</hi> their Faith: Paſs we</p>
            <p>Secondly, To the other part thereof, and that is their Fortitude; their diſpoſition and reſolution to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the worſt of Evils, for this ſo well-grounded and eſtabliſhed Faith: <hi>To you it is given in the behalf of Chriſt, not only to believe on him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake.</hi> We live in an Age that talks much of Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and with this noiſe and clamor, the Jeſuite and Enthuſiaſt (the one on the behalf of his devout Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, the other on the behalf of his Schiſmatical Anticatholicks) endeavour to run down the Church of <hi>England;</hi> making the truly Orthodox and Loyal Members thereof the only Oppoſers of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the only Confeſſors; Us the Martyrers, and them the Martyrs. But all Sufferings neither give Commendation nor Conſolation to them that Suffer; neither do all that Complain, really and truly Suffer for <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s ſake. There is a difference between Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment and Perſecution; That an act of Juſtice, This of Malice; That for our Ill deeds, This for our Good: It is not what we Suffer, but why, that will
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57621:12"/> juſtifie our Sufferings; not the Blood, but the Cauſe, that will make a Martyr: For were it otherwiſe, Then would <hi>Cromwel</hi> and his bloody Myrmidons, <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> and his band of Halberdiers (notwithſtanding their Bodies have been mangled and quartered for their Bloodſhed and Villany) be found ſtill Riding in the Hoſt of Heaven, and admitted once again to be Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Sentencers of Kings: Then would <hi>Clement</hi> the Monk who ſtab'd <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, and <hi>Ravilliac</hi> who did the like to <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, (inſtead of being juſtly puniſhed for their Murdering Tucks) be rewarded with Triumphant Palms: Then would Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven above, as well as Earth below, be fill'd with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicides, Traytors, Covenanters, Aſſociators; and little or no room left in that Glorious Palace for the Honeſt, Peaceable, and Loyal good man. Wherefore upon this account it will be fully requiſite to deſcribe the true Nature of thoſe Sufferings, that are the good Will and Gift of God unto his Church; and thereby di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh them from thoſe other Sufferings, that are the due Retributions and juſt Puniſhments of Faction and Sin. And the only Sufferings that are juſtifiable muſt be either</p>
            <p>Firſt, For Righteouſneſs, or</p>
            <p>Secondly, For <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s ſake.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For Righteouſneſs ſake; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Righteous and Juſt; that is, for not Violating ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Laws of God, or of Man; the Eternal and Natural Laws of the one, the Prudential and Alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able (yet Juſt) Laws of the other. And ſuch Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers as theſe our bleſſed Saviour (afore ever he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the Neceſſity of Suffering for his ſake) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth Bleſſed; <hi>Bleſſed are they which are perſecuted for righteouſneſs ſake. If ye do well,</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Peter)</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:57621:13"/> 
               <hi>and ſuffer for it, this is acceptable to God: But what glory is it, if ye be buffeted for your faults?</hi> If your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durance ariſe for your Faction, Sedition, Treaſonable Practices; If for violating Oaths and Promiſes, Duty and Allegiance; If for trampling the Laws of the Land under foot, and for making a ridicule of the Laws of the Church; this is no ways thank-worthy: <hi>Let none of you</hi> (ſaith the ſame Apoſtle) <hi>ſuffer as a murderer, as a thief, or as an evil-doer.</hi> Wherefore let neither the Jeſuite, nor the Phanatick, cry out henceforth of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, but rather let them know that their yoke is made heavy for the untameableneſs of the Beaſt; and the hand of Authority weighty, not for their Religion, but Faction; not for their Righteouſneſs, but Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs; not for their Conſcience, but Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy. I have joyned them together, but not one Cockatrices Egge more like to another, than theſe two Serpents are; I uſe that Appellation, becauſe they are both given to gnaw the Entrails, and to eat through the Bowels of their Parent. For what if the one be for murthering his Lawful King, for breaking all Oaths and Promiſes, and for entring into Covenants againſt him, for Lying, Equivocating, Forſwearing? Doth not the other Teach, Write, and daily Practiſe the ſame things? And what if that other out of Zeal to his Proteſtantiſm be for diſinheriting and proſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing Lawful Heirs, for that he foreſees they will not (by reaſon of a contrary Religion) be propitious to to him, or his? Is not the Jeſuite as Zealous in that very particular for his Popery? <hi>Whoſoever ſhall give his help, conſent, or aſſiſtance towards the making of a King, whom he judgeth or believeth to be faulty in Religion, is a moſt grievous and damnable Sinner,</hi> ſaith <hi>Parſons;</hi> and again, <hi>It is not enough for a man to be next only in</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:57621:13"/> 
               <hi>Blood, thereby to pretend to a Crown, but other Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances alſo may concur; which if wanting, the bare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquity, or ancientry of Blood may be rejected; and he that is firſt, ſecond, third, fourth, fifth or laſt, may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be preferr'd before the firſt. The choice of the People ſo far prevaileth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Becan) that though there be a Lawful known Heir, to whom the Kingdom rightfully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs,</hi> Tamen ſi populus praetermiſſo legitimo haeredo, <hi>yet if the People think good to ſet by that Lawful Heir, and appoint another, that other is and muſt be their Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King.</hi> And thus <hi>Reynolds</hi> warneth the <hi>French,</hi> Will ye proclaim <hi>Navarre</hi> (the <hi>Calviniſt)</hi> King of <hi>France?</hi> what is this but to advance a Dog to Lord it over Men? to proſtitute the Temple of the Living God to the Devil? to let a moſt ſalvage Bore to depopulate the Vineyard of the Lord? This I ſpeak, only to ſhew, That they are a kin, have the like Principles of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and both alike made up for miſchief; at leaſtwiſe to ſhew, who make the Firebals, and by whoſe hands they are thrown. For my part I do wiſh as well to my Religion, as any or either of them do to theirs, and Pray as heartily for the continuance of it; and will (by the grace of Almighty God) as to my ability, and the Poſt where I am placed, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it as much as they ſhall do theirs: But to put by my Lawful Prince, becauſe I ſuſpect he will call me to an account for my Religion, and thereby make me worthy of Suffering for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> nay, Bleſſed; This, my Duty, my Conſcience, my Oaths, my Religion, will not Suffer me to do. However, if at any time it ſhall ſo happen that I have either a <hi>Romiſh</hi> or a Phanatick Prince, my reſolution firmly is (to be as quiet as they will let me, or as poſſibly I can be, and) to take up with the Primitive Chriſtians practiſe (mentioned by
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57621:14"/> 
               <hi>Tertullian) Nos precamur pro omnibus imperatoribus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam prolixam, imperium ſecurum, domum tutam, exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus fortes, populum probum, orbem quietum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Theſe Sufferings that are truly the gift of God, and rewardable by him, muſt be for <hi>Chriſt;</hi> for that Religion ſuperadded by <hi>Chriſt</hi> to this former Righteouſneſs, and brought more openly into Belief and Practiſe by his coming into the World. And the Sufferings here alſo are then only juſtifiable, when they are,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Purely for <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s ſake; or</p>
            <p>Secondly, On the behalf of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> in, and relating to thoſe things that more immediately and intimately concern him; his Precepts, his Doctrines, his Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, They muſt be Sufferings purely for <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s ſake; I mean, for him, and for the Religion brought by him into the World; whereby we confeſs him on the one hand (againſt all Oppoſers) to be the Eternal Son of God, and the only Saviour of Mankind; and profeſs our ſelves on the other hand to be Candidates and Expectants through his Mercy of a Remiſſion of our Sins, of a Reſurrection of our Bodies, and of a Life Everlaſting. And I dare boldly ſay, that if you turn all the Scripture over, you ſhall find the Apoſtles, and the Diſciples, ſuffering upon no other account: And I am no leſs confident (if time would permit me to make it out) that all the Ten Perſecutions (which made ſo many Martyrs in the World, that (as St. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> ſaith) there was no leſs than five thouſand for every day in the year, New-year excepted) were upon this account, and this alone; namely, for confeſſing with their mouths, that <hi>Jeſus</hi> was the <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and that there was no other Name (nor no other Religion)
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57621:14"/> under Heaven, but that of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> by which they could be Saved. I look unto the Scripture only, and ſhall begin with the prediction of our bleſſed Saviour, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewing what ſhould befall his Apoſtles and Followers, for owning and publiſhing him in the World; to wit, That they ſhould be delivered up to the Councels, and Scourged; and purely for his ſake, and for giving te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of him to the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles (Matth.</hi> 10. 18. 22.) Paſs we thence to their real Sufferings, <hi>(Acts</hi> 5. 26.) <hi>Then went the Captain with the Officers, and brought them, and ſet them before the Councel, and the high Prieſt asked them ſaying, did not we ſtraitly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you, that you ſhould not teach in his name;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles anſwered and ſaid, <hi>We ought to obey God rather than Men;</hi> ſhewing what it was they had in command from God to Preach, and to Suffer for; and that was purely this, (Ver. 31.) That <hi>Jeſus</hi> whom they had Crucified was riſen, and that God had raiſed him up to be a Prince and a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, to give Repentance to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and Forgiveneſs of Sins. A quotation much in repute amongſt our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly Conventiclers, to patronize and juſtifie their Diſobedience and Sedition; but they ſhould firſt prove, that the Name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> is forbad to be preach'd, or call'd upon, and they purely puniſhed, for Preaching of him, and the Doctrines belonging to him, and conſequent to his coming into the World; for that, and that only was the caſe of the Apoſtles there, (as Ver. 40.) for having called the Apoſtles and beaten them, they commanded that they ſhould not ſpeak in the Name of <hi>Jeſus.</hi> Paſs we next to St. <hi>Stephen</hi> (the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to-martyr of the Chriſtian World) and we ſhall find the Multitude gnaſhing on him with their teeth, and ſtoning him, and for no other Crime <hi>(Acts</hi> 7. 54.) than
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57621:15"/> that he preached to them concerning one <hi>Jeſus,</hi> whom they had betrayed and murthered. Next to <hi>Paul</hi> (the Proto-perſecutor of the Saints, <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 2.) who when he found any of that way, (whether Men or Women) he brought them bound to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in order to their further Suffering; and the only reaſon was (Ver. 21.) becauſe they called on the Name of <hi>Jeſus.</hi> Nay, ſee what it was that this <hi>Paul</hi> (when he was Converted) firſt Preached; and verily no more <hi>(Acts</hi> 13.) than that God had raiſed one <hi>Jeſus</hi> for the Forgiveneſs of Sins, whom the <hi>Jews</hi> had ſlain. And for Preaching this Doctrine, and this Doctrine alone, it was that he was Perſecuted and Stoned; <hi>(Acts</hi> 14. 5.) for this Accuſed and Impriſoned; <hi>(Acts</hi> 24. 21.) for this ſought for to be Condemned; <hi>(Acts</hi> 25. 19.) for ſaith <hi>Feſtus,</hi> They brought no Accuſation againſt him, but concerning one <hi>Jeſus</hi> which was dead, but affirmed by <hi>Paul</hi> to be alive. So that when theſe, or any other places and texts of Scripture, are brought by our modern Sectaries to adjuſt and juſtifie the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and miſeries, that their Diſobedience and Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion brings upon them, they are utterly perverted, their Auditors cheated, and their Proſelytes gull'd into Schiſm, and unneceſſary Suffering. And indeed if ſome ſpeedy ſtop be not put to their exorbitant Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, I cannot ſee but that ere long we may have no <hi>Chriſt</hi> to preach, no Church to go unto, no King to govern us. They may talk of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> but were they all Silenced, (or would they rather be Silent, as in Duty and Conſcience they are bound to be) <hi>Chriſt</hi> would no leſs be preached, his Death and Reſurrection no leſs publiſhed; but Schiſm not ſo Sainted, nor the Nation ſo diſturbed; the King would live more at eaſe, the Church be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57621:15"/> more at quiet, and Chriſtianity flouriſh more among us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Our Sufferings are then warrantable and juſtifiable, when they are on <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s behalf; or for thoſe things which more immediately concern him, his Precepts, his Doctrines, and Inſtitutions; ſo near unto the Faith, as that our Religion would be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being notoriouſly corrupted, perhaps utterly loſt, moſt certainly altered, if there be not a full ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence to, and a ſtout profeſſion made of the ſame. Our Saviour chides the Phariſees for teaching for Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines the traditions of men, and by that very means making the Commandments of God of no effect; inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating, that there may be ſuch Doctrines obtruded upon the Church, and ſuperadded to the Faith, that may caſſate and evacuate the very Doctrines of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, deface Chriſtianity, and make the Faith another thing, and of another colour to that which <hi>Chriſt</hi> brought along with him into the World. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Anceſtors would rather themſelves ſuffer, than ſuffer a piece of Bread to be Worſhipped by them for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or in <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s ſtead; rather ſuffer their own Blood to be ſpilt, than <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Blood to be taken from them in the Sacrament; rather be broke themſelves than to bow down to Saints and Images, when God with his own tongue hath ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow down to them, nor worſhip them;</hi> rather undergo the utmoſt fury of Adverſaries than derogate from <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Satisfaction, by advancing their own Merits in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to equal claim with his; and for this they have wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily obtained the Name, and the Honour of being Martyrs. But then there are other Doctrines more remote, and rather points of Speculation than of Faith, or Practiſe; nay, the World is grown to that paſs, that there are no leſs variety of Opinions than of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and (what is worſt of all, and tends moſt to the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57621:16"/> diſturbance of the Church on the one hand, and to the diſhonour of our Religion on the other) we call all theſe by the name of Religion, and by the appellative of Faith; laying many times as great a ſtreſs upon the leaſt of them, as upon the fundamental Articles of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Reſurrection; nay, of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s being Prince and Saviour; and from theſe it is, that there are ſuch feuds and buſſels in the World, or that there is ſuch an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry of Perſecution: Whereas (God knows) it would be more for our comfort, and the Churches peace; more for the good of our own Souls, and the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of others, not to ſpread, divulge, much leſs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front an eſtabliſhment with them. Moſt certain it is, That the Apoſtles in all their Preachings eſtabliſhed no one Doctrine more (next to the coming of <hi>Christ)</hi> than that of Peace; Hence we are exhorted, To ſpeak the ſame things, to have no Diviſions among us, to be perfectly joyn'd in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgment, to follow the things that make for Peace, and (if it be poſſible) to live peaceably with all men; Telling us, That if we are Factious, we are Carnal; that if we are refractory to Government and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, we are Deviliſh; nay, that if for ſuch things as theſe we do ſuffer, we are no leſs than Malefactors; <hi>Let none of you ſuffer as a murtherer, or as a thief, or as an evil-doer,</hi> and (I may juſtly add) not as a Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick, nor as a Rebel; yet if any man ſuffer as a Chriſtian, let him not be aſhamed, but let him glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God on this behalf. I have only hinted this, to ſhew, that while I Preach for honour to be done to thoſe who really and truly ſuffer for Righteouſneſs, or for <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s ſake, I might not ſeem to advocate for ſuch mens enormities, who may be ſaid to Preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel no o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herwiſe, than as they ſet the Father againſt the Son, and the Son againſt the Father; turning all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57621:16"/> to Confuſion, under pretence of having the Goſpel of Peace in their mouths. And thus you have ſeen what thoſe Sufferings are, that are the gift of God unto his Church; and of what nature thoſe other Sufferings are, that are for Faction, Sedition, Treaſon; and not for Righteouſneſs, or for <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s ſake.</p>
            <p>Wherefore (my Brethren and Fellow-ſufferers in the Faith) be once more adviſed;</p>
            <p>Firſt, Not to let the fear of Suffering ſcare or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you from your Faith, or Duty;</p>
            <p>Secondly, That though you Suffer for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and in his Name, yet not to Suffer all that come in his Name.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Not to let the fear of Suffering ſcare or deter you from your Faith, or Duty; Be not faint nor wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in well-doing. What if the World do hate you, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe you, deſign and work evil againſt you? Is it not for the ſupport of your Loyalty, for the ſafety of your King, for the benefit of your Country, and for the continuance of a well-reformed Eſtabliſhment among you? Bonds and Fetters in ſuch Caſes as theſe, are as Chains of Gold unto the Neck, and as Jewels and rich Ornaments to the Breaſts; They add luſtre to your Arms, and enrich the Coat whereof your Poſterity will not (can not) be aſhamed. What if there be ſome ſo ſet againſt our Way, that (as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaid of <hi>Cataline) Notant &amp; deſignant oculis ad caedem unumquemque noſtrum,</hi> they mark and point out whom they intend to undoe and deſtroy? and perhaps if ſome mens Studies had been as narrowly looked into, as other mens houſes were, there might have been found black Phanaticks Liſts, as ſoon (if not ſooner) than Black Romiſh Bills. However, both akin to thoſe Papers of <hi>Caligula,</hi> (the one whereof he calls his Sword, the other his Dagger) but equally deſigned to Ruin thoſe whom he obſerved to ſtand in his way: Yet ſtill your Caſe is good, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57621:17"/> will make a Martyr (your late Royal Sovereign tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out the way) and certainly it is no ſmall comfort the Conſcience of our Innocence. It teacheth us to live in all Honeſty, and to dye without all Fear; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king our Lives, blameleſs; and our Deaths, dreadleſs; This is that brazen Wall that is impregnable, This the Feaſt that is continual, This the Light that never fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, This the Sun that never ſetteth; It walketh with thee when thou goeſt out, it returneth with thee when thou comeſt home; It is as Wine when thou feedeſt, It is as the Spirit of Wine when thou ſainteſt; If thou bee'ſt Impleaded, it anſwers, for thee; If Judged, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth thee; If Condemned, it acquitteth thee; It Enlargeth thee when thou art in Priſon, Healeth thee when thou art Wounded, Quickneth thee when thou art Kill'd; In Peace it is thy Delight, in Trouble thy Deliverance; Nay, we may call it (with a ſmall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance) the Helmet of Salvation, the Breaſt-plate of Righteouſneſs, the Shield of Faith, the Panoply of God; By this we approve our ſelves as the Servants of God, in much Patience, in Afflictions, in Diſtreſſes, in Stripes, in Impriſonments, in Tumults, in Labours, in Neceſſities; This is our Vaunt, ſaith St. <hi>Paul;</hi> our Vantage, ſaith the Author to the <hi>Hebrews;</hi> our Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſaith St, <hi>John;</hi> yea, and our Conſcience too, for ſaith one of the afore-named Apoſtles, ye muſt needs be ſubject, not only for Wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake.</p>
            <p>My Advice is,</p>
            <p>Secondly, That though you ſuffer for <hi>Chriſt</hi> and in his Name, yet not to ſuffer all that come in his Name: This is to Tolerate, not to Suffer; To tolerate all Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies, Impudencies, Wickedneſſes, Pretenſions, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Deſigners and Deſigns; no leſs grievous unto God than the Abominations of <hi>Chemoſh</hi> and of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com.</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:57621:17"/> Though you are to ſuffer for <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s ſake, and on <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s behalf; yet you are not to Suffer and to let go unpuniſhed whatſoever ſets it ſelf up in the Name of Chriſt, againſt the Faith of Chriſt, againſt the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> againſt the Defender of that Church and Faith. They that have cauſed ſo many dangerous Rebellions, ſuch Damn'd and Execrable At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts both in Church and State, are they Tolerable? Methinks we ought to repreſs their Diſloyal Practices with ſome (if not with the utmoſt) rigour. <hi>To you it is given on the behalf of Chriſt, not only to believe in him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake;</hi> but if it be given you thus to Suffer, inſtead of building Temples for the gods as <hi>Numa</hi> did, we muſt with <hi>Romulus</hi> build <hi>Aſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lums</hi> for Rogues and Villains. <hi>Ket</hi> and his Clowns, <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his Saints, will be the only Canons, at leaſt the only Canonized Tribe among us. Good men (but of them there are but a few) will be good, out of a pure love to Vertue; but evil men (of whom there is the greater number) will not be good, if it were not for fear of puniſhment. It is the Axe and the Rod, the Block and the Gallows, that teach many men Vertue. Nay, if ſuch things as theſe be ſuffered, Innocency it ſelf would no where be ſafe; Honeſty and Juſtice ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear the only Malefactors; And I doubt not but ſome of you to your coſt (almoſt undoing) full well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, That to Murder a Loyal Subject was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted good Service: to Plunder an Honeſt Neighbour a great piece of Juſtice; and to Fight againſt, nay, Barbarouſly to Judge and to Kill their Lawful Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign an act of advanced Piety; The Faithful Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters was looked upon as the only <hi>Judas,</hi> and the Loyal Gentleman as the only Malignant; Thus it was, and thus it will be, if there be none to declaim againſt, nor none to puniſh perverſe and froward Criminals.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57621:18"/> Let me therefore in this my advice (before I conclude) requeſt the worthy Patriots of our Church and State, not to be affrighted, or ſcared from their Duty (their Vigilancy and Care) by the Noiſe and Clamor of any of their Supplanters or Oppoſers; and</p>
            <p>Firſt, Not with the Outcry and Clamor that Conſcience makes; for I obſerve,</p>
            <p>That if the Faction goes out with that in their mouths, if Conſcience lead on the Party (though never ſo wicked, never ſo full and pregnant of Miſchief and Deſign againſt Church and State; Though like the <hi>Trojan</hi> Horſe it be lined with Armed men, and ſtuft up with Guns and Muſquets, and other Inſtruments of Death, yet the bare naming of Conſcience) like Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning preſently melts the Sword in the Scabbard; and cauſes the Miniſter of Juſtice (like another <hi>Belſhazzar)</hi> to ſhake, and to tremble, till the rod (wherewith he ſhould puniſh its wickedneſs) drops out of his hands. Conſcience! Oh it is a good an a tender thing; but withal it is many times Proud and Haughty, Wilfull and Erroneous, Diſorderly and very Rebellious: I could name many Kings, that even ſigh from their Tombs, and complain of Conſcience for the loſs of their Lives, and the downfall of their Kingdoms. What Barbarous Outrages, what notorious Villanies it hath acted, and ſtill continues to act, <hi>England,</hi> and the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> can well tell; Wherefore as they that deny fire to be hot, for their more certain Conviction ſhould be thrown into it; or ice to be cold, ſhould have ſome thruſt into their Boſoms; or a Cudgel to be hard and heavy, ſhould be banged with it; even ſo they that deny ſuch dealings to be in Conſcience are rightly ſerved, if in the end they ſuffer the madneſs and extremity of it. Conſcience! It is much counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced by God, and ſo are the Poor; inſomuch that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57621:18"/> he who ſhews no mercy to them, ſhall receive none from God; or he that wrongs them, (or ſeverely deals by them) ſhall be judged as ſeverely: Nay, I queſtion whether a poor Orphan, or a diſtreſſed Widow, be not as tender in Gods eyes as the moſt tender Conſcience; And yet (ſaith God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. 3.) Thou ſhalt not Countenance a poor man in his Cauſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Thou ſhalt not Honour him, ſaith the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Thou ſhalt not be kind unto him, ſaith the <hi>Talmud,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Thou ſhalt not pity him, ſaith the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> Though of himſelf he be never ſo much befriended and favoured by God, though otherwiſe to be handled gently and tenderly by man; yet if he be caught in a Contention, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in a Fault, or a Quarrel, either Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinying, or Tumultuating, ſo that the Judge muſt Judge him, then thou ſhalt not favour nor coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance him at all; have no reſpect nor regard either to the Man, or to his Poverty. And thus I conceive of Conſcience, for though whilſt Modeſt, Peaceable, and Orderly, it be to be reſpected and tendered; yet if it grow Wild and Furious, if once it be Criminal and Contentious, ſo that the Judge muſt take Cognizance of it, it muſt not then be Honoured, Advanced, or Pitied; no kindneſs ſhewn, when it grows it ſelf unkind.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Not with the Out-cry and Clamour that Perſecution makes; for let but the Offending Party guild over his Actions with the ſpecious name of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and call the Good Old Cauſe of Rebelling the Cauſe of God (making thereby the Miniſter of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice the ſpiller of Innocent Blood, and God's Avenger, the Saints Perſecutor, though never ſo falſely, yet) it dulls the ſharpneſs of the Axe, ruſts the moſt glittering Sword, and makes the moſt active Patriot to lay them by; leaving the Offenders to themſelves, leaſt in truth he ſhould be (what the cry would make him) not only a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57621:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> Butcherer of his Brethren, but a Murderer of the Saints. An Imputation ſo keen, and makes ſo deep an Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the weaker Phanſies of the more eaſie Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, that generally an <hi>omnia bene,</hi> and an Univerſal Impunity is granted by them to all manner of Diſorders (though never ſo Fatal and Deſtructive to Church and State) rather than they'll bear the <hi>Odium</hi> and Guilt of ſo bloody a charge. But the Apoſtle moſt ſtrictly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the Chriſtians <hi>(Pet.</hi> 1. 4, 15.) not to ſuffer as Evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>qui in publicas leges delinquunt,</hi> as thoſe who Tranſgreſs the Publick Laws; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or as thoſe that will play the Biſhop in another mans Dioceſs (the Preacher in another mans Cure) and thereby become Seditious: And queſtionleſs if ill they do (notwithſtanding they be Chriſtians; nay, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they paſs for Saints) as do it they muſt, whenever the Peace of the Nation and her wholſom Sanctions are violated, they may, nay they muſt ſuffer; neither need the hand that ſmites them fear a Wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for it. If theſe, and ſuch Pretences as theſe, muſt give an Indulgence or Toleration to men to Act as they pleaſe, for my part I cannot ſee, but that the wild <hi>Arab</hi> as well as the furious Zealot, The <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Janizary as well as the Chriſtian Incendiary, the <hi>Circaſſian</hi> Thief as well as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Creeper into Houſes, may claim a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. But it is time to have done, having ſufficiently angred the men of Faction; and therefore I ſhall conclude with the words, which a Famous Chancellor of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cauſed to be engraven on his Tomb-ſtone for an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitaph, (here is a Miniſter, and) there lies an Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of the Realm, who lived and dyed in Peace with all men; only <hi>furibus homicidis, Schiſmaticiſque infeſtus.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57621:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
